A Guide to the Helen C. Clarke Collection of Richmond Theatre Guild Records, 1935-1950
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Helen C. Clarke Collection of Richmond Theatre Guild Records, 1935-1950
The Library of Virginia
42762
2.35 cu. ft. (7 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased.
Biographical Information
Helen Caroline Mattson Clarke (1894-1967) was married to Joseph Calvitt Clarke (1887-1970) of Chesterfield, Virginia, and served as business manager and secretary for the Richmond Theatre Guild.
The Richmond Theatre Guild, the successor to the Little Theatre League, was formally organized on 25 October 1935 in Richmond, Virginia. Bertram Yarborough served as Director, John M. Taylor Jr., President; Stuart Bryan, First Vice President; Mrs. David E. Satterfield Jr., Second Vice President; Helen Clarke, Executive Secretary; and Robert I. Boswell, Treasurer. The first production was "Fly Away Home," in December 1935. The theatre headquarters were established at 209 West Broad Street at the Lyric Theatre in Richmond. In 1939 Robert E. Prettyman took over as Director and the theatre moved its productions to the Mosque. It is unknown when the Richmond Theatre Guild ceased operations.
Scope and Content
The Helen C. Clarke Collection of Richmond Theatre Guild Records contains annual reports and financial statements, cash book, clippings, correspondence, histories, membership information, minutes, newsletters, photographs, programs, publicity information, and reviews. These records were collected by Helen C. Clarke, executive secretary and business manager of the Richmond Theatre Guild.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Administrative Files
Series II. Theatre Productions
Contents List
- Series I. Administrative Files, 1935-1950., Extent: 1.05 cu. ft. (3 boxes). (Box 1-3)
  This series includes annual reports and fiscal statements, clippings, correspondence, membership campaign materials, minutes (1939 only), newsletters, and reports. The membership campaign material includes lists of members, advertisement campaign cards, instructions to campaign workers, receipts, and a notebook. Includes one newsletter from the Richmond Theatre Guild for 21 January 1938 and forms from the Play selection committee, with choices of play productions. Also includes information on publicity for the theatre, including letters and advertisement sent to clubs, local businesses, and newspapers promoting upcoming productions. A proclamation by Mayor J. Fulmer Bright, declaring the week of 1939 September 15 to 25th as Richmond Theatre Guild Week is also included.
  Correspondence, 1936-1950, mostly includes letters from Bertram Yarborough to Helen Clarke, after he left the Richmond Theatre Guild and became director of the Nantucket Playhouse in Massachusetts and the Grand Rapids Civic Theatre in Michigan. Also includes membership cards and flyers for the Green Room Club, a social organization run by the Richmond Theatre Guild. Also of note is a "History of the Theatre in Virginia," written by Helen Clarke.
  - Annual Reports and Financial Statements, 1935. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports and Financial Statements, 1936-1937. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports and Financial Statements, 1938-1940. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cash book and receipts, 1936-1937. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Checkbook (blank), Undated. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1938-1939. (Box 1, Folder 5a)
  - Committees, 1938-1939. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1938. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1950 and undated. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (form letter), 1938. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Early American Romance, 1938. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Election ballots, Undated. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Green Room Club membership and information, 1937-1939. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - History of the Theatre in Virginia, by Helen Clarke, Undated. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - History of the Theatre in Virginia, Notes, by Helen Clarke, Undated. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Invitations, 1939. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letterhead (blank), Undated. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Membership, Advertisement and information cards, 1935-1940. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Membership, Advertisement and information cards, Undated. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Membership, Advertisement, information cards, and instructions, 1935-1940. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Membership, Lists, 1939. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Membership, Notebook, 1935-1938. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Membership, Receipts, 1935. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1939. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newsletter, Richmond Theatre Guild, 21 January 1938. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters, The RichChap, February 1939. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newsletter, Virginia Drama News, 16 October 1939. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Notebook, Undated. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Play Selection Committee Undated. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Proclamation, Richmond Theatre Guild Week, September 1939. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Publicity, Publications, and Clubs, 1938. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Workers Daily Report (blank), Undated. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Workshop playwriting contest,, Undated. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous,, Undated. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series II. Theatre Productions, 1935-1939., Extent: 1.3 cu. ft. (4 boxes). (Box 4-7)
  This series includes clippings, photographs, programs, reviews, and tickets documenting the plays produced by the Richmond Theatre Guild, 1935-1939. Also included are several miscellaneous programs from the Musicians Club of Richmond; National Theatre (Washington, D.C.); The Nantucket Playhouse (Nantucket, Mass.); Tenth Annual Theatrical Ball Local No. 87 of Richmond, Va.; The University of Richmond Players; and The Civic Theater (Indianapolis, In.).
  The plays are arranged chronologically by date of production, with miscellaneous material at the end.
  - 1935 December 18-19, Fly Away Home, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1936-1937 Series programs. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1935 June 16-17, The Torch Bearers, Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 2a)
  - 1937-1938 Series programs. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1937 October 26-28, Her Master's Voice, Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1937 October 26-28, Her Master's Voice, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1937 November 17, Bury the Dead, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1937 December 14-16, The Cat and the Canary, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1938-1939 Series programs. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1938 January 10, Three One-Act Folk Plays: A Rogue in Bed; Judge Lynch; and The Willow Plate, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1938 January 27-29, Twelfth Night, Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1938 January 27-29, Twelfth Night, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 1938 February 21, Four on a Heath and The Gods of the Mountain, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 1938 March 8-10, Dangerous Corner, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 1938 April 11, Three Original One-Act Plays: Ice in the Anchovies; Let it be a quiet funeral; and Raising the Devil, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 1938 April 28-30 The Pursuit of Happiness, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - 1938 November 8-10, The Royal Family, Clippings. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - 1938 November 8-10, The Royal Family, Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - 1938 November 8-10, The Royal Family, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - 1938 November 18, Prologue to Glory, Clippings. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - 1938 November 18, Prologue to Glory, Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - 1938 November 18, Prologue to Glory, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - 1938 November 13-15, Ceiling Zero, Clippings. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - 1938 November 13-15, Ceiling Zero, Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - 1938 November 13-15, Ceiling Zero, Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - 1938 November 13-15, Ceiling Zero, Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - 1938 November 13-15, Ceiling Zero, Programs. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - 1939-1940 Series programs. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1939 January 31 - February 1, Death Takes A Holiday, Clippings. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1939 January 31 - February 1, Death Takes A Holiday, Photographs. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1939 January 31 - February 1, Death Takes A Holiday, Photographs. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1939 January 31 - February 1, Death Takes A Holiday, Photographs. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1939 January 31 - February 1, Death Takes A Holiday, Photographs. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1939 January 31 - February 1, Death Takes A Holiday, Photographs. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1939 January 31 - February 1, Death Takes A Holiday, Programs. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1939 February 17, The Importance of Being Earnest, Clippings. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1939 February 17, The Importance of Being Earnest, Programs. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 1939 March 24-25, The Tragedy of Julius Caesar, Clippings. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1939 March 24-25, The Tragedy of Julius Caesar, Photographs. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1939 March 24-25, The Tragedy of Julius Caesar, Photographs. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1939 March 24-25, The Tragedy of Julius Caesar, Photographs. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1939 March 24-25, The Tragedy of Julius Caesar, Programs. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1939 March 24-25, The Tragedy of Julius Caesar, Tickets. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1939 March 31, The Importance of Being Earnest, Clippings. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1939 March 31, The Importance of Being Earnets, Programs. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 1939 April 7, The Importance of Being Earnest, Programs. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 1939 May 4-6, Private Lives, Advertisements. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - 1939 May 4-6, Private Lives, Clippings. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - 1939 May 4-6, Private Lives, Photographs. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - 1939 May 4-6, Private Lives, Programs. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - 1939 May 4-6, Private Lives, Programs. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - 1939 May 17, Three Original Plays: You're on the Air; His Face Was His Fortune; and Saved by the Bell, Programs. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - 1939 November 14-16, Our Town, Programs. (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - 1938-1939 Miscellaneous programs. (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Photographs, Nora Spencer Hammer, circa 1935-1940 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, Unidentified actors, circa 1935-1940 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, Unidentified plays, circa 1935-1940 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, Unidentified plays, circa 1935-1940 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, Unidentified plays, circa 1935-1940 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, Unidentified plays, circa 1935-1940 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, Unidentified plays, circa 1935-1940 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, Oversize, Unidentified actress, circa 1935-1940 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Programs, Oversize, The Musicians Club of Richmond Presents The Gypsy Baron and Desert Song, February and November 1939 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Certificate, Oversize, Helen Clarke, 1929 June (Box 7, Folder 10)